Barbara Wright Oral Histories of Virginia and West Virginia Folkways, 1994-1996: SdArch 34
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Barbara Wright Oral Histories of Virginia and West Virginia Folkways
1994-1996
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Barbara Wright
SdArch 34
17
.2 cubic feet; 9 folders, 14 audiocassettes
1.04 gigabytes; 1.04 gigabytes (13 mp3 files)
Barbara Wright Oral Histories of Virginia and West Virginia Folkways, 1994-1996, is comprised of 13 interviews with individuals who recall life in the Blue Ridge Mountains in Virginia and West Virginia prior to the establishment of the Shenandoah National Park, as well as Wright's research materials regarding the CCC in Augusta County, photographs, and research notes on the town of Stokesville, Virginia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated by Barbara Wright on July 15, 2009.
Alternate Formats
The interview with Vastine Fisher can also be found at: Vastine Fisher interviewed by Barbara Wright, April 10, 1994, SdArch SNP-48, Shenandoah National Park Oral History Collection, 1964-1999, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University.
Bio/Historical Note
Barbara Wright was raised in Hanover County, Virginia and studied at Madison College and Blue Ridge Community College, before graduating with a degree in History from Mary Baldwin College in 1996. She served on the board of the Augusta County Historical Society, starting in 1996, and was involved in Augusta County Historical Society Oral History Project conducted at that time. Wright conducted several of the interviews while working on her honors thesis at Blue Ridge Community College, which was later published as, "Some there be which have no memorial," in the VCCA Journal 9:1, in 1994. Her research on the Civilian Conservation Corps (CCC) was the basis for her article, "The Civilian Conservation Corps in August a County, Virginia, 1933-1940," published in the Spring 1996 issue of the Augusta Historical Bulletin (included in the collection).
Scope and Content
The collection is comprised of sound recordings, transcripts, photographs, and research notes related to folkways of people living in the mountains near the Shenandoah Valley, and the history of the CCC in Augusta County. Most of the interviewees are people born between 1910-1925, who lived in or near the Blue Ridge and Alleghany Mountain ranges in eastern Virginia and West Virginia. Interviewees recall childhood stories, and memories of livestock, churches, moonshine, and the CCC. One interview includes a tour of a gravesite now located within the Shenandoah National Park boundaries. Wright also records her own responses to the interviews, and recalls stories not captured on tape. The collection includes Wright's research materials related to the Civilian Conservation Corps (CCC) in Augusta County. This includes "George Washington National Forest: a History," written by Jean L. Sattherwaite of the Forest Service Southern Region in 1991, photocopies of camp inspection reports from the 1930s, and other papers. The collection also includes Wright's research notes, newspaper clippings, and notes on the history of the town of Stokesville, Virginia, particularly related to the family of Ambrose Cramer.
The photographs depict old home sites on or near Shenandoah National Park land, including Vastine Fisher's paternal grandparents' home; cemeteries on private land above Shenandoah National Park land; photographs of the CCC camp sites at Mt. Solon and Grottoes, and other photographs that relate to interviews conducted by Wright.
Arrangement
Interviews are arranged in no particular order.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Civilian Conservation Corps (U.S.) -- History; Mountain people -- Blue Ridge Mountains -- Social life and customs; Mountain life -- Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.); Mountain people -- Virginia -- Shenandoah National Park -- Social life and customs; Country life -- Appalachian Region, Southern; Skyline Drive (Va.) -- History; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History; Shenandoah National Park (Va.) -- History, Local; Augusta County (Va.) -- History
Genre and Form Terms:
oral histories (literary works); transcripts
- SdArch 34-1: CCC in Augusta County Research Material, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Stokesville Research materials, ca. 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- SdArch 34-1: Barbara Wright Personal Comments, April 10, 1996 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA034-CS-001)
- SdArch 34-2: Nellie Blackwell Sandy, interviewed by Barbara Wright, March 15, 1996
  - Transcript and Supporting Documents (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audiocassette SA034-CS-002)
- SdArch 34-3: Viola Shaver, interviewed by Barbara Wright, February 23, 1996
  - Transcript and Supporting Documents (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audiocassette SA034-CS-003)
- SdArch 34-4: J. Wilson, interviewed by Barbara Wright, September 18, 1995 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA034-CS-004)
- SdArch 34-5: Arnold Via, interviewed by Barbara Wright, March 26, 1996
  - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audiocassette SA034-CS-005)
  - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audiocassette SA034-CS-006)
- SdArch 34-6: Vastine Fisher, interviewed by Barbara Wright, April 10, 1994 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA034-CS-007)
- SdArch 34-7: Shirley Bodkin, interviewed by Barbara Wright, April 4, 1996
  - Transcript and Supporting Documents (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Original Audiocassette (Box 1, Audiocassette SA045-CS-008)
- SdArch 34-8: George Cooke, interviewed by Barbara Wright, November 2, 1995 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA034-CS-009)
- SdArch 34-9: Wilson, interviewed by Barbara Wright, September 18, 1995, September 18, 1995 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA034-CS-010)
- SdArch 34-10: Commander William Peale, interviewed by Barbara Wright, October 2, 1995 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA034-CS-011)
- SdArch 34-11: Marvin Botkin, interviewed by Barbara Wright, October 15, 1996
  - Transcript and Supporting Documents (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audiocassette SA034-CS-012)
- SdArch 34-12: Calvin Fisher, interviewed by Barbara Wright, March 14, 1996
  - Transcript and Supporting Documents (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audiocassette SA034-CS-013)
- SdArch 34-13: Grace Simmons, interviewed by Barbara Wright, March 29, 1996
  - Transcript and Supporting Documents (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Original audiocassette (Box 1, Audiocassette SA034-CS-014)